<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<recor_doc>
		<document>
			<heading>ENVIRONMENT</heading>

			<about>Environment is a diversity of things made up of natural and artificial environment. 
			It includes chemical substances, biodiversity as well as socio-economic activities, cultural, aesthetic, and scientific factors likely to have direct or indirect, immediate or long term effects on the development of an area, biodiversity and on human activities.
			The environment provides the conditions essential to all life. This is not only true of ecosystem services such as clean air and water, but also the services provided to secure sustainable livelihoods through the use of soils, biodiversity and minerals. 
			This module explores man’s relationship with the environment and how we can manage it for the better.
			
			</about>
			<activity> </activity>
			
			<image> </image>

		</document>

		<document>
			<heading>GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES OF RWANDA</heading>
			<about>Rwanda’s physical environment can be explained by its geographical location in the East of Central Africa between 1°04’ and 2°51’ of south latitude and between 28°45’ and 31°15’ of east longitude. The principle geographical elements stretching over a surface area of 26,338 km2, which constitute the bedrock of the local environment, are particularly the relief, the soils, the climate, the vegetation and the hydrographic network. 
			</about>
			
			<activity> CLICK HERE FOR SPATIAL RELATION TOOLS </activity>
			
			<image> </image>
		</document>

		<document>
			<heading>RELIEF</heading>
			<about>Rwanda is characterized by an uneven relief with a physiographical configuration formed of steep slopes from which it gets the suggestive poetic name of “country of a thousand hills”, which briefly, but expressly explains the high altitude of the country. 

			Rwanda’s relief presents varieties. From east to west the altitude varies between 1 000m and 4 500m. The setting of this relief is composed mainly in the east by lowlands; in the center by hills and in the west by high mountains.
 
			</about>
			
			<activity> </activity>
			
			<image> </image>
		</document>

		<document>
			<heading>THE CONGO-NILE RIDGE</heading>
			<about>This is a range of mountains, the altitude of which varies between 2 500m and 3 000m. Overhanging lake Kivu, it divides Rwanda’s waters in two parts: those, which flow into the Congo basin in the west, and those, which flow into the Nile in the east. The Congo Nile Ridge is dominated in the northwest by the volcanoes range which consists of five massifs, the highest of which is Kalisimbi with an altitude of 4 507m.
 
			</about>
			<activity> </activity>
			
			<image> </image>
		</document>

		<document>
			<heading>THE CENTRAL PLATEAU</heading>
			<about>With an altitude ranging between 2 000 and 1 500m, the Central Plateau’s relief is made of hills with tops that are sometimes stretched, sometimes round, separated by deep valleys of 50 to 15m, often filled up with alluvial deposits.
 
			</about>
			
			<activity> </activity>
			
			<image> </image>
		</document>

		<document>
			<heading>THE LOWLANDS OF EAST</heading>
			<about>The lowlands are dominated by a depression of the relief, generally undulating between 1 500 and 1 100m of altitude.
 
			</about>
			
			<activity> </activity>
			
			<image> </image>
		</document>

		<document>
			<heading>THE LOWLANDS OF SOUTH WEST IN THE PLAIN OF BUGARAMA</heading>
			<about>This part of a tectonic depression of the African Rift, and it has an altitude of 900m.
 
			</about>
			
			<activity> </activity>
			
			<image> </image>
		</document>

		<document>
			<heading>ECOLOGICAL AND BIOLOGICAL ASPECTS OF THE ENVIRONMENT</heading>
			<about>Ecological and biological aspects are the elements of environment that go hand in hand. The ecological aspects of environment consist of the atmosphere; hydrosphere and pedosphere while the biological aspects include plants, animals and microorganism. Geophysical features can give details on Rwanda’s ecological aspects of environment. 
			</about>
			<activity> </activity>
			
			<image> </image>
		</document>

		<document>

			<heading>ENVIRONMENTAL CONCERN IN RWANDA</heading>
			<about>Rwanda is a land-locked country with 26 338 Km2 and a population of 8 162,715 inhabitants and an annual population growth rate of 3 %.  Rwanda is the most densely populated countries in Africa (density estimated at 302 inhab./km2) and it is administratively subdivided into 4 provinces, Kigali City and 30 administrative districts.

			Rwanda’s natural resources –land, forests, waters and wildlife– have embodied the countries main sources of households and national income, providing the basis for farming, fishing, household energy production and tourism. Over time, however, these resources have been seriously depleted and degraded, due to high population pressure (CCA, 2000). This population is overwhelmingly engaged in subsistence agriculture on small family land. Rural population density on arable land is 929 people per Km2  (MINECOFIN, 2001).   

			One result of these trends has been an increased scarcity of arable land, which has had multidimensional effects on Rwanda’s natural resources, including: soil erosion and exhaustion; depletion of arable land; the conversion of pasture and marginal land to crop lands (leading to a decrease production of manure and a consequent decline in soil fertility); the conversion of wetlands to arable lands (resulting in flooding, sedimentation, loss of wildlife habitats); and encroachment on Rwanda’s remaining natural forests; which are reservoirs of biological diversity and endemic animal species such as mountain gorillas.

			Currently over 96% of Rwandans depend upon fuel wood for domestic energy. This fuel wood dependence in combination of rural settlement and farming activities has resulted in considerable deforestation. Statistics from the 1980s show that Rwanda’s wood consumption outstripped its wood production by 2.3 million cubic meters annually. From 1958 to 2000, Rwandan natural forests have been reduced to about 30 % of the original coverage area (MINAGRI, 2000).

			Overall Rwanda has been and continues to be caught in vicious circle where increasing pressure for land and fuel wood results in high level of environmental degradation, which in turn fosters the decline in agricultural production. The longer-term losses caused by deforestation are both high and irreversible (CCA, 2000).

			In Rwanda, land constitutes a resource of inestimable value. It occupies a first-rate place in the national economy since farming employs more than 90% of the working population and contributes about 93% of exports.

			However, the small size of the country makes land a very limited and, hence, a coveted resource and subject to degradation. Indeed, out of a surface area of 26,338 km2, 52% only is usable, representing approximately 1,385,000 hectares. Marshes suitable for agriculture would add to this about 165,000 hectares.

			Rwanda has an abundant network of rivers some of which supply drinking water. Water is also important in several sectors of the economy such as agriculture, industry, services, energy, etc.

			Water installations in different sectors have an environmental impact. The destruction of natural water reserves and bad farming methods result in the reduction of capacity and the time of water retention by the soil, and this may lead to the drying up of the ground water. 

			During the long dry seasons, some water sources run dry, the flora dry up, causing food shortages for the people. During the rainy seasons, water becomes a danger and causes considerable damage because of the erosion due to water run-off. Erosion causes also pollution of water sources and rivers, lakes and environment.

			</about>
		</document>

		

		
		
		<activity> </activity>
			
			<image> </image>

		

	</recor_doc>